Zewdu Mogesse

Data Scientist

zewdu94@gmail.com | +31-628727099

With 4+ years of experience in IT industry, an enthusiastic Data Scientist with business acumen eager to contribute to team success through hard work, attention to detail, and excellent organizational skills. A clear understanding of Machine Learning, experienced working with real world-data, excellent in communication with different clients, and storytelling with data. Motivated to learn, grow, and excel.

Professional History

Data Scientist collaborator

Oct 2020 - Present

LaNubia Business Consulting, Full Time

Helping LaNubia in designing short and long term projects, workshops, and coaching for its clients in Logistics, utilities, consumer goods, and other sectors.

Data Scientist

Sep 2019 – Aug 2020

UNILEVER, Full Time

An application in the data pipeline form that can take process information, extract semi-structured data, structure, compare, map, and scaling was developed.

Data Scientist

Jun 2018 - Sep 2019

JHERONIMUS ACADEMY OF DATA SCIENCE

Worked in multiple short-term projects for different companies in energy, water, construction, high tech, consumer goods, and health sectors.

Network Performance Analyst

Jul 2013 – Jul 2015

ETHIO TELECOM

Analysing the collected data, identifying core problems regarding quality, coverage, congestion rate and traffic, and proposing a solution.

Education

Professional Doctorate in Engineering: Data Science

Eindhoven University of Technology, 2018-2020

Master of Science: Computer Science (Data Science Specialization)

University of Trento, Italy, 2015-2017

Certifications

- Big Data Integration and Processing
- A-Z Machine Learning using Azure Machine Learning (AzureML)
- Neural Networks and Deep Learning
- Data Science: Natural Language Processing (NLP) in Python

Highlights

- o Python, SQL
- Business Consulting
- Data Science
- Data Analysis and Visualization (Dashboard and graphs)
- Predictive Analytics
- Cloud technologies

Relevant Skills

Python	00000
SQL	0000
BI tools such as Power BI	0000
and Tableau	
Machine Learning	00000
Deep Learning	0000
Web Framework: HTML,	0000

Residence

Eindhoven

CSS, Flask, CMS

Professional Work Experience

LaNubia

<u>Data Scientist | Blaricum | Oct 2020 - Present</u>

- Designing short and long term projects, preparing workshops, and find coaching opportunities by collaborating with different clients in logistics, utilities, consumer goods, and other sectors.
- Projects:
 - Billing collection analysing, prediction, and optimization
 - Predictive maintenance

UNILEVER

<u>Data Scientist | Gelderland | Sep 2019 - Aug 2020</u>

- Developing an application that can extract, structure, and create master table for process information.
- Developing an application that can compare two processes in different factories, map them with corresponding equipment, and apply scaling rules on it.
 - Data Science Techniques: Unsupervised machine learning algorithm (Associative rule mining), course graining-based analysis, process mining, maximum common subgraph, and social network analysis (SNA)
 - Tools: Python, Dash Plotly, and Power BI

JHERONIMUS ACADEMY OF DATA SCIENCE

Data Scientist | North Brabant | June 2018 - September 2019

Short-term Projects (from 6 weeks – 12 weeks)

- o Analysing the spare parts lifecycle in the supply chain process at ASML
 - Data Science Techniques: EDA, Visualization, Process Mining, Rule based machine learning techniques such as association rule mining.
 - Tools: Python, Disco, and Tableau
 - Result: An application that can visualize and show spare parts relationship was developed.
- Information Extraction on intoxication and psychiatric Issues through ambulance data visualization for GGD
 - Data Science Techniques: Pre-processing, Exploratory data analysis, and Data visualization.
 - Tools: Python and Dash Plotly (a Python framework)
 - Result: An interactive dashboard for analysing, extracting, visualizing intoxication and psychiatric issues.
- Automating negotiation and pricing strategy for DAF PACCAR Parts.
 - Data Science Techniques: Supervised machine learning algorithms such as K-nearest neighbours, Decision tree, Quantile random forest, and A/B testing
 - Result: Partial automation of price negotiation

- Data lake for consolidating and analysing data for Brabant Water
 - Data Engineering Techniques: AWS, Google Cloud, MS Azure, Apache products such as Kafka, Nifi, Flume, and Hadoop ecosystem are assessed.
 - Result: For on Premise solution: Designed two architectures using Apache Kafka as a stream ingestion and batch processing using Hadoop HDFS with MapReduce. For cloud solution, Microsoft Azure was recommended for Brabant water in terms of cost, security, and flexibility.
- o Predicting the cooling down curve during asphalt production processes at Heijmans
 - Data Science techniques: Visualization, Supervised machine learning algorithms (XGBoost) and Artificial Neural Network (ANN)
 - Tools: Python and Tableau
- Electricity Theft Detection for Enexis B.V
 - Data Science Techniques: Supervised machine learning algorithms linear regression and Random forest.
 - Python framework: Dash Plotly
- Condition Based Recoiling of Radiant Coils Based on the Furnace Operating Conditions for Dow Benelux B.V.
 - Data Science Techniques: Unsupervised learning such as PCA, K-means, EDA, and Visualization.

ETHIO TELECOM

Network Performance Analyst | Ethiopia | July 2013 - July 2015

- Collecting network quality data using drive test equipment from different area of the country.
- Analysing the collected data, identifying core problems regarding quality, coverage, congestion rate and traffic, and proposing a solution.
- o Communicating, managing, and evaluating the work of each section of the company.
- o Installing LAN (Local Area Network) based on customer request.